software engineering radio episode 89
Joe Armstrong on Ilana this is software
engineering radio the podcast for
professional developers on the web at s
e - radio dotnet se radio Prince
irrelevant and detailed discussions and
interviews on soft engineering topics
every 10 days thanks to our audience and
the partners listed on our website for
supporting the clock
[Music]
hi everybody welcome to software
engineering radio so here is some
information about the SU radio get
together as you know this is our open
space conference is an autumn of 2008 it
will happen up on October 16th and 17th
in a thing called close to home path
needs by plugging Germany it's actually
due directly next to us by plugging
Airport which doesn't mean much it's a
very small airport but anyway we would
like you to come we would like to have a
lot of interesting discussions there
you'll have to submit a position paper
to team and as you radio dotnet so we
can see you actually have interesting
ideas to talk about we want this to be
really a lively discussion well we also
have a nice dinner
sponsored by X they agreed to sponsor
the conference and make sure we have a
nice dinner on Saturday so why don't you
visit the website and look at the
details and then join us at the SU radio
get-together conference you can do as a
great favor by mentioning SU radio on
your own blocks and other and web sites
helping us to make su radio more widely
known is very useful to us and be sure
we'll thank you for doing it okay I
guess so that's enough for the meta
stuff let's go ahead with the content
this time we were talking to Joe
Armstrong I'm always tempted to say Jo
Rowling because he's the mr. Erlanger I
guess so welcome Jo thank you before we
actually delve the topic I'd just like
to say thank you to try fork the the
organizers of Jo because they gave us
this room inside the try four offices so
we have a quiet spot to do the interview
which is always useful
so Jo why don't you give us a little
brief overview of what Erlang actually
is how it was created and why anybody
cares today what's the big deal well
what is healing gentle in a nutshell I
suppose today would be its parallel
programming without the pain parallel
programming is perceived as being
something which is rather difficult
and I think this is due to not the
problem of parallel programming in
itself but the way that people perform
parallel programming there are there are
basically two models of parallel
programming one involves the idea of
shared memory which is protected by
mutexes and locks and that method of
roaming is extremely difficult
Erlang takes a completely different
approach and uses what's called a pure
message-passing paradigm so there's no
shared data and in Erlang everything is
represented by a process processes
communicate by message passing which
makes concurrent programming a lot
easier so so the message is that err
Lang is a language which makes
concurrent programming painless okay and
processes are obviously not the same as
operating system processes it's very
lightweight uno they're very lightweight
objects they're they in Elling processes
belong to the programming language and
not not departed the operating system
there is this this general idea of
actors I guess that's close yeah okay so
when was Erlang created what was the
context in which it was and what kind of
systems was it built for it's difficult
for the first date to it because it was
never a project to make a new
programming language but the work that
it derives from started in 1986 and it
was done and the computer science lab at
Ericsson at the time we had the problem
of just really trying to find a better
way of programming telephony and of
programming big switches Erickson's core
business and we just started tinkering
around with different programming
languages to see how we could program
telephony now telephony is a problem
where you have hundreds of thousands of
people all connected to the same switch
all doing independent things and so the
problem is very naturally concurrent and
inside Ericsson there was a strong
tradition of building concurrent systems
which also fault tolerant there the
other aspect of the problem with is that
unlike desktop systems and commercial
systems telephony systems have to be
upgraded without taking them out of
service so I think when we started work
we we were looking at a way of handling
massive concurrency hundreds of
thousands of people being controlled by
one switch
we also wanted these systems to
basically run forever because if we
needed to change the code we have to do
this without stopping the system uh-huh
so it said about 1986 we we started
looking at how to do this and I think
the first version of what you could call
air lang was was in 1987 and this I
wrote in in in prologue well I started
with prologue which and I really like
prologue right one new weird language in
an old even weirder language sort of
weird language beautiful language I
don't really understand why everybody
doesn't use it the prologue isn't very
good at certain things it's not real
good at doing concurrency so all I would
add concurrency to prologue and so she
could have lots of Prolog processes all
running at the same time cause it was
extraordinary and it's inefficient yes
the programming model was was was very
attractive so that's how it's daunted
mhm the focus is on concurrency so the
reason why it's becoming well popular
hyped relevant these days is obviously
the multi-core yes stuff right yeah I
think really ok Alan's a language which
is 20 years old and for about 18 of
those years it was just being used
internally inside Ericsson so so
nobody's really interested in it a few
sort of devotees on the outside world
used it but he didn't have any wide
Spade and wide spread popularity I think
Kim when you have concurrency which or
threads or anything like that which run
on a sequential processor you don't
actually have concurrency you have you
have multi scheduling yeah they're the
operating system schedules between
different processes and that's not real
concurrency so there's no benefit
actually your premise will go slower if
they're multi-threaded because the extra
overhead of scheduling but yeah but when
you have a true multiprocessor things
actually go that start going faster yeah
and that's a radical change so you and
your presentation you call this a real
significant paradigm change that needs
to have changed another better approach
to actually yes absolutely
I mean I think the the other thing that
happened was from about 1986 from 1985
to 2002 sequential processes got faster
on average by about what did I say 65%
per
something a lot yeah and from 2002 to
2004 that slowed down to 20% of the year
and the reason for that was that chips
got bigger and bigger and bigger and the
the clock frequencies got greater and
greater and greater and so in about 2002
we got to a situation where in one clock
cycle you couldn't reach all of the chip
and that was a fact the metal issue yes
it was predicted by some hardware guys
in in 2000 and and they wrote a paper
saying the end of the road for
instruction level parallelism what what
that means is that chips as from about
2002 actually go slower because the
solution to that problem is to not have
one whacking great big chip which gets
bigger it's to break it into small cause
on the same chip yeah so actually
programmers had a free lunch from you
know all throughout the mid 80s and 90s
they could add more and more bloated
features to their code their code could
go slower and slower and slower and they
were saved at the end of the day by a
faster clock speed yeah I mean I you
must remember that that you know Amstrad
CPC 40 40 megahertz back in 1985 and now
we are 5-2 gigahertz sir so programmers
actually didn't have to do anything now
I don't know if they were aware of that
fact you see and I think when their boss
sort of congratulations and said wow
your new programs got a lot more
features in it see you know it's not
slower you are an amazingly smart
program and I think a lot of program is
a key believed that it was due to their
a super smart code and they ignored the
fact that the processor had got faster
yeah so so that trend stops in 2003 what
happens then is that the sequential
processes start going slower there so if
you want--if pretty different yeah and I
think there's gonna be I think let's see
what will happen I think after a year or
two years don't be this gap which people
will start to notice and they after
three or four years and then the funny
things gonna happen
in 2009 Intel according to their roadmap
will bring out the kafir a processor
which it's got 32 cores and some poor
programmer is going to be sitting there
and they're going to have performance
problems with
program and the boss is going to look at
the cpu measurement on the machine and
see that it's let's say it's using one
of these 32 cores at 100% and he's going
to say hmm what a moment you're telling
me you've got performance problems and
yet we're using three percent of the CPU
come on in order to use that over 97
percent of the CPU you have to write a
true multi-headed application there now
you know Java programmers know all about
thread-safe applications and they also
know that when you go from a sequential
processor to a parallel processor the
program probably won't work well
actually I don't think they do know this
yeah but they will you two scientists
know this because because the program's
interleave in a different way and a
whole new new load of bugs are going to
come out yeah okay so in in the book you
recently wrote which is called a
programming Erlang pragmatic programmer
thing we put it into show notes you
started actually by motivating a new
approach to programming which you call
concurrency oriented programming and you
didn't say it's object-oriented with
concurrency or functional with
concurrency you kind of tried to coin or
what you did coined this new well not
moniker for a completely different
approach
so can you characterize what this
concurrency oriented programming
approach means as a whole what what are
the ingredients to making it yes it's a
style of programming where you use
concurrency to structure the application
I mean that's that's a real answer and
it's a style of programming which which
maps on to the real world because we
live in a concurrent worlds and if
anybody who tells you that we don't is
is an idiot I mean wherever you look you
see you see things happening in parallel
and people are walking around a room
cars are buzzing along on a motorway way
something like that and to model that in
a sequential language is a complete
nightmare it just doesn't make any sense
so so as I see the world
I see objects which which communicate I
mean we're sitting in a room having an
interview and and you know fir to model
that this is Marcus each one process Joe
is another process I'm sending messages
to him you know he's just sent me a
message a visual message the message was
move the microphone nearer to your to
your mouth because because the
microphone was drifting off there's a
message
and we don't have shared memory yeah we
had shared memory Marcus and I would be
a Siamese twin and we would communicate
you know through some annual passage but
we don't work like that the world
doesn't work like that and modeling it
like that I think it's a disaster this
is a shared memory programming which
here a deep sort of well there are two
models of concurrency this shared memory
processing and there's message-passing
processing so so the concurrency
oriented programming bit that's the
model of what we're doing you see you
have programming languages and then you
have modeling languages if you take the
world of objects the programming
languages are object-oriented languages
and languages like Java C++ and the way
you model the world the way you think
about the world is in terms of objects
so if you go to the airline world the
programming language is based on on pure
processes and message passing but the
way we model it is a concurrency model
and we matter the concurrency model from
what we observe in the real world okay
so the primary thing here is to share
nothing no shared memory actors are
completely isolated yeah however there
is an additional tweak to it and I mean
Erlang is a functional language it
doesn't which doesn't have any immutable
state yeah so there is also this thing
of requiring no locks on a much lower
level yeah so so how does how does
immutability and this functional modify
nothing approach play into this
the reason shared memory programming
models are difficult is the two parallel
processes can access the same area of
memory and at the same time and make
changes to that memory and that's that's
a notion of mutable state if you have
immutable state then variables in a in a
language cannot be changed once they've
been set and I guess what we call assign
wants variables having been given a
value they can never ever be changed
there that means that the process itself
cannot change them but more importantly
it means other processes come and change
them since all the processes can't
change them you don't need to lock these
data structures so everything you can
run in parallel yeah when I was reading
the book I actually wondered how
important that feature really is because
if you had mutable state within an actor
and used message passing between them
then you would still achieve the
actual level concurrency and no shared
property right yes so so I was wondering
how well if I built an active library on
some other language that and forced
those properties then I didn't need a
functional language that had the
immutability concept on language level
right or is it literate deeper do it
that yeah I mean I think it's it's
probably a historical accident that the
that err Lang is that the individual
processes are immutable and that that
actually reflects the prologue history
yeah if it had started off C or
something like that with added
message-passing yeah we could have still
done say a version of C MPI yes
something like that yes which isn't a
message passing interface but there are
additional benefits to having non
mutable state so in the book I say when
you debug a program you have an
additional benefit because when you if
you if you set a variable only once yeah
you later observe that it's incorrect
there's only one place in the program
where you can happen yeah but if it's
getting updated all over the place you
don't know which of these occurrences
was the one that led to the error yep so
it is actually very easy to debug mm-hmm
good point something well you have these
actors which serve as the active
ingredients of a concurrency oriented
program now if you build a virtual
machine for Erlang or compile or however
you do it actually is a compiler
interpreted or yes well it's both again
it's the first version was a pure
bytecode interpreter and that became a
32-bit threaded word interpreter and
then a group of topsail University built
a hyper compiler which was a
high-performance airline nice acronym
yes so we could hype it up and so today
what we distribute is well actually yes
the Machine changed to became called
beam which was first of four bogden's
Erlang abstract machine in fact we had
we had three or four of these machines
all sort of named after ourselves in
typical modesty and yeah that's how the
current version is is a 32-bit threaded
machine in a rather light forth yeah
with the native code compiler if you
wanted so so in some sense
and that's what I was trying to get at
the virtual machine of course uses
threats probably threat pools of stuff
to do with dance to a virtual pool seals
to threats from the operating system and
then it does everything itself so okay
so processes or I mean air Lange is much
more like at the runtime system is much
more like an operating system okay then
the normal run time for I mean the
normal run time for programming language
rather small for because everything is
done with instructions and through the
compilation process we're nailing the
runtime system is enormous because it's
it's doing an awful lot of what the
operating system is doing in fact the
operating system just basically manages
files and sockets for us and gives us a
large amount of memory when we start
then we do it all ourselves yeah we
already mentioned MPI briefly in passing
it so the question is why is everybody
doing shared memory and are you the only
guy who the only community who does the
message passing thing so the questions
is there are other approaches that or
other languages are the tools that that
use the same kind of approach to to
concurrency there are but I don't think
there that's maturity Erlang Airlines in
kind of leading the pack when it comes
to message passing concurrency and I
think the the reasons for it I've
actually got nothing to do with speeding
up things on multi course because that
said that's a modern phenomena yeah the
the original reasons have to do with
fault tolerance so if we back off back
to 1986 what we were trying to do then
is to build a fault-tolerant system so
so I think software people don't really
understand fault tolerance well I can't
where people do so so so the first I
used to get a lecture
I still do give a lecture where I said
well if you're gonna make a
fault-tolerant system you need two
computers yeah it looks strangely at me
and I said well you know come on if one
computer crashes you're screwed so you
actually need two computers or more or
more yeah I mean you can have three or
four or five both of them might crash
and so if you're Matt let's let's take a
very simple world it's only got two
computers and we want to make a
fault-tolerant system it's pretty
obvious that you have to copy all the
data from one computer to the other that
you need to do a recovery if computer
number one crashes you take over on
computer number two
and that means you can't have any
dangling pointers you must have copied
everything you need from computer one to
computer to incase computer one crash
it's true so so that's the reason for
copying everything it's got nothing to
do with concurrency it's got a lot to do
with fault tolerance yeah and so and so
that's the kind of rhythm Tetris of
effort for Erlang that has an inevitable
cost because yeah you people people want
to say things like well I would like
fault tolerant to cost nothing in the
case where the system doesn't crash but
but that's just not possible because if
you if you make a fault on a system you
need two computers you need to copy all
the data over if they don't crash you
could have just had a dangling pointer
you could have copied less data but it
won't work in the presence of errors the
additional benefit which we saw years
later was once we copied everything we
no need to lock everything and these two
machines can work in parallel on that
data really I don't think that's that
thought wasn't in our heads you know
back in the mid mid 80s it's interesting
to see we had a couple of episodes on
distributed systems and in the
distributed systems world it's it's well
known that that that message passing is
a good way to do it
obviously you can't have shared memory
over physical well you're Sweden
Australia example yes so in addition to
sequential Erlang which is a functional
programming language with pattern
matching we'll talk about that later and
concurrent Erlang which allows you to
basically spawn every function execution
into a separate actor
there is also distributed Erlang so how
is that different
the models not different that's why we
have concurrency went to prison in this
model we just have message passing it
uses what we call location transparency
this is just the idea of if you know the
name of somebody can send them a message
it's like email or popping a letter into
the post
how you actually implement that is it a
kind of well it's not a detail but you
mean what the hard the VM does it yeah
so so here are two alternatives or three
four alternatives one way of doing it is
to have two virtual air language running
on the same physical processor these are
these are separate address spaces with
their processes and everything then the
probe
themself manages the namespace they say
well I want to start a process in node
number two or node number one and you
can have as many nodes as you want
that's very convenient because you could
you could put say ten nodes on one
processor one sequential processor and
you can test a distributed application
then you can deploy it in a real
distributed application by moving these
nodes to physically separate a
computer's possibly in different
countries that's one model of
distribution the other is that you map
these nodes automatically on to the
cause of a multi-core computer and then
you don't need to know about the nodes
and and there's a different completely
different version of em of yelling
scheduler which will just schedule a
randomly onto one of these that was not
random is a round robin scheduling yeah
but but the details don't really matter
and in the implementation we will
improve those algorithms I think so in
that version of a Lang the Aling
programmer sees a world where there's
only one node and the virtual machine
Maps processes on to the physical cause
in the CPU makes actually no changes to
their program but that's the nice thing
actually I mean if you want to evaluate
a function on another in another actor
you just basically say spawn and then
you specify the function and if you want
it on another node you say spawn
function then at name of the target no
that's pretty neat yes and just all the
data in the closure just Weezie's over
to the appropriate now we're having to
do anything
yeah nice ok so so let's leave the
concurrency aspect behind for a moment
and let's look at the fault tolerance
aspect we've right by the time we
broadcast this we've we will have had
the double episode with Bob henro and
fault-tolerant systems so you listeners
should know what it's all about to build
a fault-tolerant system and some of the
patterns and so in in Erlang there is
this thing called let it crash let it
die
yes so what's your model towards fault
tolerance there the model of fault
tolerance is the fundamental model is
that of handling errors remotely not
locally the reason for that is back to
our if you go back to our two computer
situation we have two computers one of
them crashes the error must be handled
on the second computer
computer crashes we can't handle it on
the first there is no computer to handle
it on yeah so so this introduces very
early on the notion of remote error
handling so if if process one crashes
process - we'll fix it up so it's a
basically we try not to fix up the error
in process one okay there is a there is
a try-catch except things other thing
inside one process just because if it's
a trivial error and and you can deal
with it then you do do so yeah the the
model we build is is basically what's
provided in the language is is a
reporting mechanism so if one process
dies another process gets an error
message and so a this process dies you
can link processes one being the
supervisor off the edge right so we it's
all like a human organized a story we'll
get with it again yeah with with yeah
because it's very easy to understand we
have we have workers and we have
supervisors yeah the workers do the jobs
and the supervisor just watches the
workers if a worker dies the supervisor
gets informed and he starts a new worker
so the workers are not supposed to fix
errors they're not there you know we
even have programming rules it and we
tell them I not allowed to fix errors
this makes a very very clean programming
model so the it's very strange in all
languages apart from Erlang you're
encouraged to do defensive programming
in helping we're not encouraged to do
defensive programming we have what
people call happy case programming we
only program the happy case what the
specification says the task is supposed
to do you see I mean one of the troubles
which I wish I met early in programming
was when writing code from a
specification the specification says
what the code is supposed to do it does
not tell you what you're supposed to do
if the real-world situation deviates
from the specification this is an
enormous class of things it doesn't tell
you what to do if it doesn't follow the
spec so what are the programmers do they
take ad hoc decisions this is crazy this
is this is lunacy and this leads to
about 30 40 50 percent of all code is
this error checking code to allow for
the cases which are not in the
specification now the specification
doesn't tell you what to do so the
owling approach is
crash if you deviate from the
specification specification you crash
and the supervisor process detects it so
the workers going along and it says
basically it says you know it's like a
really top-down strict brain-dead
organization where the worker encounters
a situation they don't know what to do
right and so they die and their
supervisor gets a message hey I've died
because this thing happened that's out
of spec so what is it what does a
supervisor do he says make sure all the
invariants are obeyed
now the invariance of things like
closing files closing sockets cleaning
up behind you yeah it doesn't matter how
an error occurred doesn't it's it's
irrelevant because we we put it right
with the invariance afterwards now this
error goes into the error log when we
look at the error log we can say ok what
happened was this worker gave up because
this funny thing happened there and then
the system was put back to rights again
and then we can make a design decision
do we wish to code for this care or is
it so rare then it's never gonna happen
again yeah yeah and that brings us
nicely to the next point so if this
thing really has a well to use the
correct terminology I think a fault
somewhere in the code you might want to
replace this module actor or whatever so
that's where if you want to run the
system forever you want you you need
this dynamic on the fly the update
ability that's something else that Lang
brings yes and in fact wait here's the
funny thing when you have deep
concurrency no language lots of
processes things like code upgrade
actually become easier than in a
sequential language because I mean let's
imagine we've got a million processes
and you know a thousands of them are
executing code that's got some little
bug in but the other 900,000 I don't
know how many we don't want to bother
those guys okay so they can just carry
on doing what they're doing if we can
track down the thousand processes have
got the bad code in them we can change
the code in those ones and leave all the
rest alone okay now if you only have one
process that's a problem that's a
problem
yes frood so one impressive number I'm I
don't know where I read it was
probably in the book was that using this
approach you achieved nine nines for
some kind of this was a this was an
Ericsson asynchronous transfer mode
switch called the XD 301 that figure of
nine 9's is kind of bloated around in a
lot of blogs and there and doesn't
represent an average behavior it
represents the best case behavior that
was observed once and British Telecom
observed this and reported it when we
asked him I think for detailed figures
or you know was this a systematic study
no it's more apocryphal than hard
science but it's the prof maybes it is
the sort of top of the mountain you know
I'm not saying that all systems run like
that but yeah but aiming at seven nines
or something like that it's that's
realistic so if you want just to since
we talk about actual real achievable yes
comments let's briefly go back to the
concurrent thing what what are the what
is the scalability do you really get
linear scalability how much does this
depend on what you program on your
structure of the program what's some of
the best practice is to to make a
program scalable yes right this is very
early days because just just not with
there aren't many multi-core processes
with large numbers of process yeah and
the the largest one you can get your
hands on it's probably the Sunmi agarra
which it's got what is it eight it's got
eight I think they're up at 64 cores now
but I've played with the the eight core
version with four hypertransport law
which some say is equivalent to 32
Hardware threads now what we see there
is programs that have a large amount of
computation and a small amount of data
in the messages scale linearly up to
about say 20 processors above 20
processors sorry not processors 20 cause
of course when we go up from from 20 to
32 cores the curve flattens off a bit
and I don't think we understand why and
I you know somebody might understand why
we have to investigate the cache
behavior and things like that but that's
very encouraging then the entry level to
concurrent programming
Dule cause I mean you can't you can't
really investigates you don't get many
plots on a graph when you've got two
points you can't just get two points but
it's very encouraging Americans ship the
product on a name annual core AMD which
was only twice as fast as as the one
that was running on a single core and
everybody was absolutely delighted I
mean so so here the programmers are
because you know our programs are all
written in Erlang we're sort of ready
for concurrency yeah so when the when
when they ramp up the number of cores we
tweak the program a bit long in and
measure how fast it gets so so we see
this as a great commercial advantage
sure and to make it concurrency already
it basically meant that you should have
as many actors as possible because if
you have few processors course it's well
just schedule on several ones and if you
have many it's just gonna fill up it's
not only that you have to you have to
get rid of the sequential parts oh yes
there's something called aminals law
which very easy to understand I mean if
let's aminals law says well for example
if 10% of your application is sequential
then you'll never be able to go faster
than 10 times and the reason for that is
if you think about it 10% is sequential
90% is concurrent but this 90% can be
just made to shrink down to 0 with
enough processors left with the 10% but
you can't do anything about
so really chasing the sequential code
out of your application is the thing
you'll have to do to make it go really
really fast and of course you can only
do that if the overhead of making
something concurrent is Nicklin it is
very low yes and that's the whole point
that's the point yes I think you're
absolutely right there that's a key a
key observation because on the chips
there are two types of concurrency
there's instruction level parallelism
which is deeper pipelines
and then you've got thread level
parallelism and that maps onto
multi-course so there isn't actually
another parallel mechanism there are
parallel ility man that sounds awful but
there's not another mechanism for
parallelism there so really now since
you're doing thread level parallelism
the programmer has got to make the
decision is it worthwhile the effort
of spawning a process on a new physical
processor because if it's a very small
computation it's not worth the effort of
the Sindelar off to another process and
I think only the Harlequin made that
judgment and I'm pretty sure that's
right because right since the 1960's
have been research programs to
automatically parallelize programs
chiefly Fortran for supercomputing
applications and these projects have
never succeeded well they succeeded in a
minor sensei if they've managed to speed
up things by 15% and that's that saying
ok we'll let the compiler or the room
analyzers program figure out what we can
do in parallel
I think the programmer is much much
better at doing that they know well they
should know a good programmer has a
performance model in their head and they
say well I know this is a big
computation I know it's isolated from
that so I'll spawn it off in a separate
processor it's just that the the nuts
and bolts of doing that in C or Java is
extremely address you know it's painful
and it's very easy in LA so when I read
the Erlang book and even more when when
when I wasn't your talk yesterday one
day I got the impression rolling isn't
really a language it's a system an
operating system with the language of
course but there is a lot of
infrastructure that makes all these
things possible it's almost like a
little bit of an application server I
mean if you compare that to some of the
enterprise application servers you will
see many commonalities yeah um but in
order to build real systems you actually
do deliver in the package
additional infrastructure which there is
a little bit talk about the OTP
framework I think we have an unfortunate
naming here because actually I don't
think I've ever said airline wasn't the
language hailing is the language or I
said that was my impression yeah so
what's OTP and what's the runtime system
I think if to give you an analogy I
think if you say well ok airlines like
see the runtime systems like UNIX and
OTP is like Ruby on Rails it's an
application framework got a very unsexy
name I mean if we just called OTP OTP on
Rails you know everybody would be using
it
so it's ro TP is an application
framework and it's it's got all the kind
of goodies you need to build
fault-tolerant systems so we're familiar
with application frameworks think that
Ruby on Rails or help you make web
applications but we're not familiar with
application frameworks that help you
make unsexy things like fault tolerant
software that runs forever so that's
what ap is it's it's it's it's a Erlang
on Rails or whatever you like but for
building fault tolerant applications and
the runtime that's the operating system
those are the ingredients as the
database I guess and some kind of
probably server component so the main
ingredients yes as you said there's a
there's a database now that's a very
interesting database it's it's tailored
for real time use but I mean it reflects
its heritage it was it was done for
telecoms application here for Ericsson
we use it in telecoms application so
it's Ram resident and well that's not
strictly true it's you can define tables
in it it's it's a DBMS it's rather
unique I think in that once you've
defined the tables you can you can
specify where physically the tables are
and how they are forgiving you can say I
want a ram replicated table on two
machines and that's for fault tolerance
or you might Ram replicate on two
machines and disk replicate on one
machine so you spread the tables over
three machines or do machines or or you
might have a fragmented table you spread
over 50 machines if you if you have a
closely large data set so it's very
flexible and of course it understands
about Ellington data terms object
database yes you can put it you can put
any tuple I mean you don't have to
serialize something you know if you want
to store an XML parser e in the database
it's a single instruction and bang in
goes your XML path tree yeah this is no
messing around it's it's an object store
yeah okay so then let's look at the
other extreme we've looked at all the
infrastructure or distributed
concurrency blah blah blah let's look at
sequential Erlang no it's a functional
language can you give us a little bit
some some pointers to what some of the
interesting features are it's a
dynamically typed functional programming
language so functional language will
program it into a number of different
schools all functional programming
languages
based on the idea of immutable state no
site and immutable States another way of
saying they have no size and and you
know what you learned in school was that
side effects especially when they're
hidden are evil yeah that's why you know
that's what you're doing Java all the
time put them in a method you hiding for
a set your programs are crap and a
function play drivers don't believe in
that they believe in something called
the lambda calculus the lambda calculus
is a pure calculus for how you perform
computations that has spawned off
several kind of families of functional
programming marriages you you have the
polymorphic strongly typed languages a
school and things like that and there
you and then you've got the the language
of data type system they're still safe
that language like scheme and airline so
so Airlines in this dynamically typed
part of the functional programming
language but it still has all these
notions of higher-order functions
immutable states I think that's a proper
man image it's a proper member of the
functional programming language
community so we see different functional
languages which I think are different
appropriate for different tasks sir can
you give us a very broad intro to what
pattern matching is because that's the
concept that Java folks and probably
mainstream people don't know yep pattern
matching is we don't use if statements
and and case statements and what we do
actually but but to a much lesser extent
and the normal programming though we
just write patterns dude unmatched and
that's in the function in the function
declarations there are different
variants of the same function with
different parents that match to guess
it's a way of doing polymorphism a
separate rule polymorphism in CSS now
what what the pair matching compilers do
they take these patterns and they
actually compile them into trees of if
statements and switch statements and
they're but they do it probably in a way
that is more efficient than you or I
could do so that they optimize these
things though the main consequence of
pattern matching is that the programs
are extremely short mm-hmm because the
programmer doesn't have to think about
do I write a switch statement or a case
statement or if statement they don't
write these they just write the patterns
and the compiler produces these things
for them
okay so I think that was all the
technical stuff yeah let's look a little
bit about to wrap up slowly and how the
language was designed I kind of thought
that you know you don't design the kind
of well okay I mean you know you were
kind of visionary in some sense what
concurrency okay so what I'm about
trying to get here is that the problem
well maybe if it wasn't designed we
shouldn't even call it a process so what
were the sequence of accidents that led
to Erlang well as I said we we started
off I joined this really newly started
computer science lab at Ericsson back in
about 1986 and we just got I think we
the first people in the company to get a
UNIX system because people said oh you
can't use UNIX or sort of virus it does
not be connected to the rest of the
corporate networks nobody believed in
UNIX in those days and we had a VAX 11
750 so basically we interpreted computer
science is just programming telephony in
in every programming language that there
was a free implementation for the backs
11 750 our definition of computer
science and we just sort of tinkered
around so this wasn't a process what we
actually did we we programmed the same
problem which was just pots we had a
little - we had a little hardware
telephone exchange a PAP X which we
controlled from these different
languages and we wrote telephony in
Eider and concurrent include and Prolog
and small talk and ml than all these
languages and we actually published some
research on this and we we just saw how
easy it was to program so what happened
then was I was sort of grafted into this
project and I everybody was doing their
own little ways of programming so I use
Prolog and added processes to it and
this very slowly sort of you know one
day it had gotten a name you know we
actually said well this is sort of a
little programming language and then we
thought oh let's try it out on some
users and we managed to find some users
and
and they said ah this is great I mean
they they liked it they were really
enthusiastic and things kind of did it
along and yeah they liked it it wasn't
fast enough they wanted features we had
in the features show so you grew the leg
yes and in that day I mean that was just
me and them and you know a complete
rider rewrite of the system took the day
or 20 minutes it wasn't it wasn't long
and you know my boss biana used to say
what's what's air Lang is worth whatever
Jo defines it to be today there was
never a big specifiy why didn't they all
this kind of when I give a lecture and
we say here are the requirements for the
language and that's that's an
after-the-fact construction and
afterwards to explain what we've done we
never had a set of requirements
well implicitly we had a Mississippi I
think I think the culture you know we
work for a big telecoms company the
culture sort of you know the
requirements were sort of seeping out of
the walls they were in the culture yeah
and so we built this we tried it out on
some users after about a year I worked
on it alone and then Robert the eddying
joined me and Robert as usual said can I
make a few changes to your program yeah
sure you know and then typical Robert
what was he rewrote everything in I I
think what was left after you made a few
changes from one commented Joe started
it's changed every single line of code
and then there were two of us and then
about a year later Mike Williams came
along and and there were three of us and
at that stage they wanted it to go
faster that made it they decided that
they could deploy Erlang if if it was 80
times faster 80 88 to zero because it
was a prologue interpreters very slow Oh
so we kind of scratched our heads and
thought how do we make it go faster and
we decided to then do a bytecode
interpreter and that's written in C I
guess today or well yeah so so we at
that stage I started writing a bytecode
interpreter and I wrote
Prolog and of course he didn't go fast
he went slower going from about Oh the
Prolog Burton went about a thousand
inferences per second I went out of four
inferences a second at aha yes but it's
a cunning plan we'll replace the slow
interpreter with a C program and then I
started writing seek now I'd never
written C before I used to write Fortran
until Mike wanted buchen Jo that's the
word see I've ever seen tried to look at
local yeah and so Mike Mike came along
and he wrote an emulation see it might
was pretty good at C so and he really I
think he he and I sort of he taught me
quite a lot about C and and Mike Mike
was always Mike had a lot of experience
with with concurrent languages and so he
said well the performance of a
concurrent language is predicated by
three things it's it's a context
switching time it's a message passing
time and it's the time to create a
process so these are fundamental you
know in any programming mode you start
with something that's fundamental and
you you implement that very very very
very well yeah and then you build your
tower on top of it and so what Mike did
in the emulator there was he wrote the C
and then he turned on the optimizer and
he printed out he did it again and again
and again but these kinds of low-level
virtual machines it makes sense to dump
the details because it scales can write
so we tweaked the details there and then
we made the first bytecode interpreter
and that was that was actually that was
before the the JVM and things like that
we deployed it and it I can't remember
what it was it was more than 80 times
faster it was a hundred times faster or
something and the product team said they
had revised - 280 and that started this
long road of sort of rewriting and
making it fast well and that that
carried on until it was turned into a
register machine and open Houseman took
over the table and beam yes that's right
and he
he re-engineered the machine for
register machine and we got researchers
it and so he class affixed remained
after four years and added things like
the real-time database and he added
district distribution would always plan
distribution but we never actually
implemented it I mean it seemed just you
know we've just got messages and things
so it must be easy to implement because
[Laughter]
it sort of grew from this very rapid
prototyping cycle where everything took
a day to rewrite the complete system and
now it must be up in a I hate to think
you know six months or something Sharlee
optimized yeah okay to wrap this thing
up why don't give us a little
description of what the community is
today how the book is going you know yes
given what's behind the hype these days
no you know I mean it's gone berserk
it's crazy I mean if you look at if you
look at Reddit and things like that you
would think they're only two languages
around this house cleaner they're
fighting out for my chair sure but
that's I mean that's that's people who
get turned on by programming languages
people seem to be flocking to the
language I mean if if you if you just
search fair lang blogs you know there's
four new ones you know go go into Google
and do blog search on airline you'll
find sort of four new ones a day not
saying I'm not saying they're all good
some of them are extremely good some of
them are kind of not good but that's not
the point the point is is this this
interest that sir and then we've got one
or two flagship applications
you know telephony applications and
databases aren't sexy stuff forever kind
of boring yeah I think the flagship
application is a jabbered which which is
a jabber server and that was that was
written completely you know I think the
exciting thing is can can a lang spread
so the outside its commodity can we see
spontaneous growth from people who've
just picked it up off the net and yeah
we're seeing lots of that we're seeing a
lot of companies being formed that use
it I think we're seeing a lot of
companies that use it and make money
we're seeing a lot of companies that put
Java competitors out of business
you know this is and people know about
that the word is spreading yeah
venture capitalists know about it so
they're financing the company that's
very exciting
so this blog post by Ralph Johnson who
suggested that Erlang might be the next
Java so it seems to be taking off really
yeah I don't know if that's true they
also found a little bit maybe a bit of I
think I was thinking about this and I
think Ellen might be kind of in in in
the way that languages are it might be
like small talk because if what happened
with small talk was small talk with the
language that did object-oriented
orientation right they got it right and
the good ideas were taken from small
talk and grafted on to see there and and
and create and of course the creation of
language is like like Java now small
talk always had this passionate
community that said what we do
object-oriented programming right and
all these other people just stolen a few
of the ideas and not stolen the lived
these ideas in their languages so what
might happen with earning is is that it
has this passionate community that says
what we do concurrency oriented
programming right and that other people
craft these ideas into their languages
so we might see Java the java plus plus
yeah that has the airline concurrency
model you might have heard about the
Scala people yes with the actress
framework into it and got really good
concurrency yes so that's yeah but I
think they would really have to I don't
know how they've done it and well they
also have closures and some of the mess
some of the pattern matching case for
re-engineering this from as I said
earlier the in the Erlang virtual
machine you have to you have to start
with the process spawning mechanisms
with the context switching times with
the message passing times really
low-level in the version which air and
then you build it up if you don't have
instructions in the virtual machine to
do that earths you have to emulate it
there
that's very inefficient so if you want
to re-engineer a virtual machine like
the JVM or something like adding
instructions to create processes and
things and then build something on top
of that I don't think you could graft in
the the existing infrastructures I mean
the trouble with Java is if you if you
say well let's make Java plus plus
so that we can use all the libraries but
the libraries are using this shared
mutates not really going to work but but
re-engineering it could work well as
long as as it has curly braces I think
that's going to be the next big language
anyway okay did I forget to ask anything
you want to say no this is really cool
because it's a DSL which is my kind of
pet peeve at DSL for parsing bits in a
byte stream so yeah give us the heads up
yeah the bit syntax is something that
was added to Erlang but by a class of
extreme as an afterthought and tonydd
wrote got I think it is as well and they
what they observed was a lot of time
they're just unpacking data structure I
mean that packing unpacking bits yeah
out of words
so you know if you ever tried to extract
seven bits out of the middle of a 32-bit
word you do sort of X bit shift left by
eight bits and zero X F F now what the
heck is that in you know how you do that
yeah it's horrible in India and of
course you get it wrong and actually I
with my approach wouldn't really be
since I'm into this DSL stuff to write a
DSL that specifies exactly what I want
so that's exactly what we did we we
extended pattern matching over bit
fields yeah
so now you can say you know this is
seven bits is three bits this is two
bits it has nine bits and and that gets
compiled into pretty efficient code so
in the book
my favorite example in the book is is of
course it's an MPEG 3 streaming media
server which elements the shoutcast
protocol and what we have to do there to
get it right is to synchronize the
server with the the actual MPEG 3 frames
now this is just about as low level as
you can get but it's written in a
language is a high level language so you
just you just define the bit pattern
which defines a sync frame in MPEG 3 and
then you just trundle down the data
looking for this yes you found it you
just stay in sync and the code is really
easy to understand and it's a nice
example of something where if you put
the specification on one side and you
put the code next to it listeth it's
isomorphic yeah so very easy to its when
I was in your talk
I think macros criticism from
intentional was also there we looked at
each other said hey this is a really
good example for yourself in yeah I
think one of the sort of things where
you see in a lot of prayer that that can
be grafted onto a lot of programming
land I've always wondered why and why do
regular expressions go over bites very
easy to make a regular expression
manager that map's it over it's it's
very useful yeah absolutely especially
if you're in this kind of low-level area
yeah okay Joe thank you very much for
being on the show I appreciate it was
very interesting thank you bye
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website at
SD - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
by on the website or you can advertise
for se radio for example by clicking on
the Digg reddit delicious and Slashdot
buttons to contact the team leaves an
email to team and SI radio net or if
it's specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can read and react to your
comments this episode of software
engineering radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under Creative
Commons license
please see the website for details
thanks to Charlie crowd and the pot site
music network for the music used in this
show the song is called Vegas hard rock
shuffle